Good afternoon. Hello everyone and
welcome back to True Health Tuesday. My
name is Maria Jose Hmel and uh I am very
glad and happy to be back with you for
another true health Tuesday. And uh as
you can see from today's um title for
today's presentation,
we are going to be talking about setting
effective goals and increasing
self-control because we just finished a
cycle of presentations on diabetes and
all the other complications that are
associated with diabetes and insulin
resistance. So we talked about all these
different things and um uh complications
and conditions and the different things
that are related to lifestyle that we
need to implement in our lives. So when
I do the uh when I used to do the
seminar on diabetes, I used to
incorporate this presentation as part of
the seminar because we could have all
the knowledge in our head about what to
do.
But sometimes we have all the knowledge
in our head and we still have a hard
time doing what we know how to do. Uh so
sometimes it's very important to talk
about how to do it. Not just what to do,
but now how to implement these changes.
So that's what we're going to talk about
today. Before we start, we're going to
go ahead and have a word of prayer. So
let's pray. Dear heavenly father, thank
you so much for another beautiful day
and another opportunity to have True
Health Tuesday. And we ask you to be
present in today's presentation and the
technology. We ask you to uh help us so
that everything will go well with the
technology. And we ask you to also bless
everyone who will connect today. Uh we
ask that you send your Holy Spirit to
not only uh be with me so that it is not
my words but yours but also to bless
everyone who will hear this presentation
that you will impress their hearts as
well so that uh they your spirit will
help them uh to implement everything
that will be said and that they will
also spread this word and share it with
others in Jesus name we pray. Amen.
All right. So, we're going to go ahead
and start it because this is a very
important concept. You know,
self-control is part of the fruit of the
Holy Spirit, as you know. So, we're
going to talk about how to increase
self-control. But again, as I always
say, this is only going to be
educational. Nothing that I will say
will be meant to be treatment or medical
advice. So I always start with that.
This is very important to make sure that
we talk about this. This is not we're
not going to talk about diabetes today.
So this is less going to be less medical
that previous presentation. So that's a
good thing. Uh but I also want to make
sure that I include my spiritual
disclaimer as well. Uh everything that I
say I always try to as I've said before.
So this might be repetition for some of
you, but for some of you that are
watching maybe for the first time, I
always try to make sure that my
presentations go along with Isaiah 8:20,
which says to the law and the testimony.
So I always try to present things that
are according to the law and the
testimony as Isaiah 8:20 says, which I
interpret that to mean the Bible and the
spirit of prophecy as an Adventist,
which I am a Seventh Day Adventist. I
interpret the uh law and the testimony
to mean the Bible and the spirit of
prophecy.
uh and I recommend that we all are
knowledgeable of what the the Bible and
the spirit of prophecy talk about in
regards to health. The other thing that
I also want to make sure is that my
presentations have a solid scientific
evidence or base. And as you can see
from the graphic that you're looking at
right now on the screen, to me, the
lowest type of scientific evidence is
expert opinion or what people just say.
Um whether it's on social media or the
internet presentations even so call
experts make sure that when you hear
other people talk about health and uh
you know whatever presentations people
do make sure that they have solid
scientific evidence so that we have
credibility when we share information to
other people who might not be
Christians. So I would recommend that
when you share information especially to
non-Christians that you are presenting
things that have solid scientific
evidence as well. And so when I give
presentations I always try to present uh
like studies and that are good quality
studies. And you can see right here from
the graphic that the best quality
studies are metaanalysis and systematic
reviews. Meaning these are studies that
are compilations of other good quality
studies hopefully and the good quality
studies are usually the randomized
control trials. Uh these are usually the
best quality studies. But when it comes
to nutrition sometimes you have to have
different kinds of studies. So either
randomized control sty trials along with
other types of trials, epidemiological
uh studies that could be cohort studies
uh and other types of studies. So when
you have a lot of different studies
together, then you put together things
such as metaanalysis and systematic
reviews and then you have good quality
data. That's why they're at the top of
the pyramid.
And then if you share that with people
who might not be believers, then you're
giving yourself more credibility.
Uh and I think that could make that can
distinguish us. And I think Adventist we
have good
uh I think we have very good
status. Uh I think we have uh in the
world people look at us differently from
other maybe denominations because we
have things such as Lomal Linda um and
uh people look at us differently. We
have uh maybe we're part of the blue
zones and we have you know uh this
medical center down in Luminda and we
are well known for these things. We have
the Adventist health studies and we have
things like that. So I think we could
continue to distinguish ourselves
because we have the health message too.
There aren't a lot of denominations that
have this. So we could continue to
distinguish ourselves with to to
differentiate ourselves as long as we
have these um good quality information,
good quality health message. Anyway, I
digress. We can then go ahead and
continue uh to present. I want to go
ahead and present why I believe in good
scientific knowledge because it says
right here I bas you know I put my my
trust in the spirit of prophecy and it
says right here in Christian education a
knowledge of science of all kinds is
power and it is in the purpose of God
that advanced science shall be taught in
our schools as a preparation for the
work that is to precede the closing
scenes of earth's history. I've read
this many times, but some of you might
be watching for the first time. So
closely is health related to our
happiness that we cannot have the latter
without the former. A practical
knowledge of science of the human life
is necessary in order to glorify God in
our bodies. Now remember that glorifying
God in our bodies is part of the first
angel's message. So this is very very
relevant for these times. All right. So
we are ready to start our message for
today.
Now we have said a lot of things in the
last previous presentations
and uh when we talk about health, why is
it that sometimes we really really know
that we need to eat healthy foods, we
need to do better, we need to you know
control ourselves and eat a healthy
diet. But why is it so hard sometimes?
Why is it that we think we know what we
need to do and we seem to not be able to
do the right thing? Well, I want to read
to you a few quotes. By the way, I want
to say hi to Andrea from New Brunswick,
Canada.
Hi, Andrea. Thank you for um thank you
for joining us from Canada. and hi to
all our friends from any country that
you're joining us. Thank you for joining
us. Um, thank you for joining True
Health Tuesdays. Anyway, I really wanted
to share with wanted to share with you a
few quotes that I think are super
important. This is from councils on diet
and foods. And look at these interesting
quotations. Okay? Uh quotes from these
from this book. One of the strongest
temptations
strongest temptations that man has to
meet
is upon the point of appetite.
One of the strongest temptations
that man has to meet is upon I would say
the strongest nowadays, but you know, I
don't know if you you agree with me on
that, but I think it's the strongest
nowadays. Anyway, the second one says
the following. Satan is constantly on
the alert
to bring the race, the human race fully
under his control, his strongest holen
man is through the Oh, here it is. See
the his strongest
strongest
hold on man is through the appetite
and he seeks to stimulate
in every possible way.
Boy, it seems like she was looking into
the future, doesn't it? It almost seems
like she was looking into the future and
able to predict what was going to happen
in the 21st century. Even starting in
the 20th century,
able to see what TV,
social media,
you today you walk into the pharmacy,
it's not like just medications in there.
You walk into
uh a gas station, it's not just gas in
there.
We are constantly bombarded
by stimulation of our appetite. Yes or
no?
Yes or no?
He is constantly trying to stimulate the
appetite, trying to control us through
the appetite. That is the strongest hold
on man.
Yes or no? Next one. The controlling
power of appetite
will prove
the ruin of thousands.
When
if they had conquered on this point,
they would have the moral power
to gain the victory over every other
temptation of Satan
if they had just been able to conquer on
this p on this one thing.
That's how important this is.
This one thing, this one thing you can
call it different names.
Willpower, self-control, determination.
It is so difficult.
So difficult to have it.
When I used to work at a community
clinic
as a nutritionist, as a clinical
nutritionist,
I would have children as young as 10. I
think I've shared this with you many
times probably
uh ped pediatrician you know I used to
work with adults obviously with chronic
diseases
diabetes high blood pressure
um high cholesterol
these things
are typical of adults
type two uh diabetes it used to be
called adult onset diabetes now it's no
longer called adult onset diabetes now
It's called type two because now even
children develop type two. So it's now
called just type two. Now not no longer
called adult onset diabetes.
Well when I used to work there at a
clinic I had children uh sent to me with
type two diabetes already diagnosed by
the way but also high cholesterol, high
blood pressure,
fatty liver. When I was a young child, I
don't know how many of you might be
around my age. Now I'm gonna have to say
how old I am. Uh, you know, past 50s,
let's say, middle-aged.
How many of you had you classmates that
had
high blood pressure,
high cholesterol, type two diabetes,
and I had the parents with the children
and we would talk about
the diet, of course, you know, I would
go, you know, over the questionnaire
typical that we had to do to for our
recall or whatever other questionnaire,
you know, trying to figure out, well,
you know, what what are they eating?
And most of the time the parents already
knew
what the child should be eating. Yet
it's not it's not like we don't know.
Most people already have a concept at
least of what we should be eating
more vegetables. It's not a mystery to
most people. Uh we probably shouldn't be
eating uh what you're looking at on the
screen. Junk food is called junk food
for a reason, right?
Most people already know fast food is
not great, right?
But I mean sometimes people would give
me excuses, right?
uh like well okay so I would ask things
like um you know you know the the child
for instance had soda or something and
they would and the parents would say
well you know I have the soda in the
fridge because well why would I serve
the visitors when they come home if I
don't have the Coca-Cola or whatever in
the fridge
what why what would I serve my visitors?
Do we really need to serve visitors
sodas when they come to visit us or you
know I have such a physical work you
know I do a lot of physical you know
work at my you know their job is very
very physical maybe construction or
something so I need to drink soda you
know so I can keep up with my work do
you do you really you know things like
that so sometimes I' I'd hear uh excuses
I would say excuses Or they would say,
"I hide the chips all the way up above
the fridge." Literally, I hide them. And
you know, little Johnny, I'm just
saying, you know, I'm making up names
here. Little Johnny goes up, cry, climbs
up all the way up and still gets the
chips.
What would you say
if you were
Why do you have the ch Why do you even
buy them?
These foods are literally like drugs.
We're going to talk about this. I'm very
I am very convinced that I'm going to
talk about food addictions
two weeks from now. The next
presentation is going to be about food
addictions because these foods Yes,
Tyra. Exactly. See, you were reading my
mind, Tyra. Thank you. These foods are
literally drugs.
How can you hide them? They're going to
go get them.
You can't just buy them and hide them,
you know, that's not going to work.
So
yes, so most people literally know what
they need to do, but sometimes we don't
do it. So let me show you another
example of this point. So I think I've
mentioned before that, in fact, I've
shown you this very um study in the
past. This is from the 1990s, early
1990s. Dr. Dean Ornish who became very
famous for this very reason was one of
the first who showed with research that
coronary heart disease was actually
reversible.
Prior to that, if you had coronary heart
disease, your doctor would say, "Well,
this is not curable. You're going to
have it for the rest of your life. We're
going to give you medication to control
and hopefully, you know, you won't die
immediately. You know, we'll try to keep
you alive for a while, you know, with
medication or whatever. We'll do some uh
intervention, some surgery, blah blah
blah. All right. But in the early 1990s,
after some years of doing this
lifestyle, intensive lifestyle changes,
as you can see, that was an
intervention. That was the study that he
did. And so basically they put people on
this lifestyle program and they showed
that the plaque
what I'm talking about is this
cholesterol plaque that starts to
accumulate inside the arteries. That's
what starts to block the arteries.
That's what causes eventually the heart
attacks. Right? So if the artery is
blocked if your coronary arteries block
get blocked obstructed that's what will
cause the heart attack.
Well, if you change your diet when this
intervention was more than diet, they
put people on an exercise program,
stress management, quit smoking, all
these things. Stress management too, by
the way. So, all these things eventually
what they saw, and I'll show you the
picture actually. Here's the picture.
What you see right here on the screen
before and after. Notice in between the
yellow lines, you see that's the plaque.
Basically this is a a picture of the
artery and uh when you see it between
the yellow is the plaque and before it's
thicker and after you see a reduction of
the plaque. this when this was
published. All right. Wow. It's a
revolution in cardiology because wow
this is the first cause of death number
one cause of death in the country.
Now back in the 90s it wasn't the
numbers we have today. Today is almost
700,000. I would say close to if not
already at 700,000. pretty darn close to
700,000
people a year. Every single year die of
this one cost, heart disease
every year.
Every year, two years, 1,400 three year,
you know, 2 million after three years. I
mean, every single year.
And so when this came out,
wow.
Wow. Because up until that time,
incurable. No cure for this. And all of
a sudden, what? We can reverse this.
Are you serious? This is insane.
So, Dr. Nedley, I remember hearing this
a presentation. Dr. Neil Nedley
he said he went to one of these
conferences medical conference the
presentation where the where these
results were given
and it was just wow everybody was like I
can't believe it wow
and uh he thought to himself Dr. Netley
he says in one of his presentations I
remember hearing this and he says wow
this is amazing this is 1992
early 90s
and he thinks to himself in 25 years
nobody will have a heart attack 25 years
I mean that's a lot of time if you think
about it but that's how long it takes
for research to trickle down into
medical practice
25 years no one will die of a heart
attack. We have the cure.
1992.
How many years have gone by?
More than 25, right?
So, nobody has a heart attack now,
right? Nobody.
No one. No heart attacks. They're gone
forever.
Oh, wait. They are heart attacks and
heart disease is first is still the
first cause of of death in this country.
Why?
We already have the cure.
By the way, that's not even the only
study that found it. The previous study
was intense lifestyle.
This one from Dr. Caldwell Eselstein was
just the diet. No exercise, no stress
management,
no stop smoking, nothing. The only thing
they did was the diet. And you can see
right there, first line, abstract
purpose, plantsbased nutrition. That's
it. The only thing they put they did was
put people on a plant-based diet.
That's it.
And
this is what they found.
Well, figure one shows profusion,
better, you know, better blood flow
through the heart. That's great.
Figure two, reversal of coronary artery
disease.
You can even read the caption of that
figure. Okay. Figure two.
Coronary angography reveals a diseased
distal left anterior descending artery.
the widowmaker.
And you can see how thin that artery
looks. It's because it's very
obstructed. It says before, I labeled
it. It's picture A
before. Very thin.
It's because it's very obstructed.
Okay. Following 32 months of a
plant-based nutritional intervention
without cholesterol lowering medication.
By the way, no medication.
What?
Only the diet.
Following 32 months of plant-based
nutritional intervention without
cholesterol-lowering medication.
Please read it. The Because I'm not
lying. You can see it with your own
eyes. Okay? The artery regained
its normal
configuration.
Are you looking? Are you seeing what I'm
seeing?
Cuz you can also see with your eyes the
after. Compare before and after.
The artery looks 100% like a baby's
artery.
It's amazing. It's unbelievable.
It's amazing.
So, what we can see here is the cure,
you guys.
A plant-based diet. Nobody should be
dying from a heart attack anymore.
So, why are people dying from heart
attacks then?
So, there is a psychologist you guys
psychologist not cardiologist.
very famous.
His name is Roy Biommeister.
He is the most cited psychologist in the
country from the University of Florida.
And he says the following very
interesting
thing. He says, okay, he says,
lack of self-control
is the number one cause of heart
disease.
What?
I thought it was a diet. I thought it
was lack of self-control.
Lack of self-control
is the number one cause of heart
disease. Now, that's his specialty, by
the way. He studies
willpower. In fact, you can look up his
name, Google it. He's written books. I
think the title of his one of his most
famous book is in fact willpower.
Lack of self-control is the number one
cause of heart disease. Why? Because we
already have a cure.
cure,
but we're not doing it.
So, if you already know what to do and
you don't do it, it's no longer a
physical thing.
It's here, isn't it? It's not a problem
of the body anymore. It's a problem of
the what?
of the what
isn't it?
What do you think? Put it in the chat.
Put it in the chat. What do you think?
Anyway,
I'm going to show you.
I'm going to tell you a story. I'm going
to tell you a story.
Here
is another person.
This gentleman
is also a medical doctor.
And as you can see from the picture,
this picture is very very old, right? Or
looks old anyways, black and white. So
this gentleman, his name was Graham um
Dr. Evers Graham. That was his name.
He lived back in the 30s4s and he was a
surgeon.
He became very famous
because he performed a surgery in in a
in a man who had lung cancer
but he had lung cancer in only one lung.
And so he performed a surgery and took
out the lung with the tumors and left
the other tumor or sorry left the other
lung in that person and this man and so
the man survived with only one lung and
I don't know if you knew that I don't
know if you can knew that that person
can live with one lung but this man did
and so he became wow that's super
interesting and so he became famous he
also became famous because he had these
machines, these contraptions in a lab.
He had this lab with these machines that
basically he put cigarettes in these
weird contraptions that took out
basically the smoking machines kind of
took out the tar the smoke and the tar I
don't know from the cigarettes. He
extracted tar from the cigarettes. And
this tar was like a thick uh dark thick
uh substance. And he would smear it, I
guess, on these well, I guess, lab rats
or mice. And he would put it on the lab
rats or mice, I guess. And uh the the
little mice developed tumors,
cancer.
And then he would compare the tumors
with patients. And he realized that the
cancer that the the mice were developing
was the same as the patients that were
smoking. So basically he made the
connection. This remember you guys back
in the 30s and 40s the this was before
the general surgeons report from the
what 1964 or something where it was
definitely established that smoking
produced lung cancer. So back in the 40s
and 30s and that time it wasn't nearly
as accepted that smoking caused cancer.
Right? So this was highly debatable I
guess at the time and people weren't
100% as convinced I guess. So he was the
one who started to make the case for it
by performing these studies. So anyway
that was another reason why he became
famous.
So this man was very famous and
obviously as a surgeon he was uh well
off he was a very intelligent man
wellstudied right and so
he was famous he had money he was uh
intelligent smart he had everything in
life successful man as you can imagine a
successful person
so anyway he had everything in life
except he had one problem. He had a he
had a bad habit. He had quite a really
bad habit actually. Can Can you think of
what bad habit he might have had?
In fact, he had a really bad habit that
caused him a big humongous problem.
Can you guess what bad problem?
bad habit he might have had.
Do you want to guess?
Well, this man
actually smoked cigarettes.
He smoked
cigarettes.
In fact,
he was
addicted.
Oh, sugar. That's a good guess, Tyra.
That's a very good guess because guess
what? Sugar is just as bad as
cigarettes, I would say.
But in this case, Dr. Graham was
addicted to cigarettes, knowing full
well, right? He was the one doing the
studies. He was the one looking at
tumors in both humans and animals.
And he smoked.
And guess what? Not only did he smoke,
he developed cancer.
And here where the story goes even more
sad.
He writes a letter. This is how we know
the story because he writes a letter to
his best friend who was also a physician
and his best friend's name was Dr. Alton
Ashner who's also a famous doctor,
famous surgeon from New Orleans.
And the reason why we know this is
because Dr. Ashner gives a testimony or
reflection later on in life. I guess he
reflected
Adventists have a good stop smoking
program. Yes, they do. In fact, that's
how my that's how I entered the the
church because my dad was a smoker. And
when I was like 13, 12, 12 years old, uh
we were invited to a fiveday smoking
program in an Adventist church and my
dad went and he stopped smoking thanks
to an Adventist smoking program. Yes.
Too bad they don't do them as much
anymore. There's still people who smoke,
but I remember even when I was a child
and I was going to a non-adventist
church uh school, I remember seeing the
posters every year uh for a day of non
not smoking uh sponsored by the
Adventist church. This was when I didn't
even know about the Adventist church,
but every year there was a poster in my
school of no smoking day or something
rather sponsored by the Adventist
church. Anyway, as I was saying, Dr.
Ashner wrote a uh or Dr. Evers Graham
wrote a letter to his best friend, Dr.
Ashner. And Dr. Ashner, many years
later, reflected how sad he felt when
Dr. Evers Graham wrote him a letter
saying
um basically said, "I have cancer." He
told him, "I have cancer. I have cancer
in both lungs.
and it is malignant
and I won't be living much longer.
Basically, it was an advanced cancer in
both lungs and doc Dr. Ashner the friend
said he felt so sad because reflecting
upon the fact that his friend was so
smart, was so intelligent, had such a
great career, money, fame, success,
I mean everything. He had everything a
man could ever desire.
But he was going to die soon
because he lacked one thing.
You know what he lacked?
He lacked self-control
because he knew full well for years
how bad smoking was.
He if anyone would know, it would be
him. He was the one doing the most
advanced research at the time on the
dangers of smoking. If anyone in the
world knew how bad smoking, it was Dr.
Evers Graham.
and he wouldn't quit smoking.
Why?
Why don't we do the very thing we know
we need to do? We still don't do it.
Why?
Well, guess what, Doc? um nearby where I
live. I live in California, West Coast,
and not too far from here, about an hour
and change, less than an hour and a half
from where I live, there's a very famous
university called Stanford. And back in
the 1970s, they studied this. They
called it delayed gratification. The the
ability to delay gratification is called
self-control.
And they studied this through a very
famous experiment. I don't know if
you've ever heard of this. It's called
the marshmallow
experiment. I don't know if you've ever
heard of it. If you haven't, I invite
you to look it up later because it's
interesting. It's very, very
interesting. It's a series of studies
done with children back in the 70s and
the children were young
between ages of four and six more or
less as as you can imagine children at
that age love marshmallows as you can
imagine right and so the experiment
consisted in the following thing. They
would put a child about this age in a
room
with a table, chair, and a plate. And
the plate at first had one marshmallow.
And the researcher would say to the
child, "Hey, um, here's a marshmallow on
a plate and, oh, I have to go somewhere
and I will be back in 15 minutes."
But if you look, there's a marshmallow
here. If you don't eat the marshmallow,
I'll wait for me. Don't eat the
marshmallow. If you don't eat the
marshmallow, I'll bring you back and
I'll give you two.
But if you eat the marshmallow, I won't
give you anything else. Okay? No more
marshmallow if you eat the marshmallow.
But if you wait and don't eat it, I'll
give you two.
Can you wait the 15 minutes? That was
the test.
So these kids four to six years old,
what do you think they did?
Can kids wait 15 minutes to eat a
marshmallow? What do you think?
Do kids have self-control
enough
to wait?
What do you think?
Well,
some do, some don't, and some are in
between.
In fact,
if you Google
the marshmallow test, marshmallow
experiment,
Stanford University,
and go to images.
It's hilarious, you guys, because you'll
see pictures of some of these. Some do,
right? Ros Russellin said some do. Yes,
that's right. Some do, some don't. And
somewhere in between because some of
them were able to wait five minutes and
they couldn't wait anymore. They they
they would eat it. Some of them waited
like 10 minutes
and they just couldn't wait anymore. And
they would do the most
hilarious things to distract themselves.
In fact, okay, if you go to images,
you'll find some pictures of of what the
kids had to do to distract themselves.
Okay? And so, some of them would,
you see some of these pictures, right?
Some of them would sing. I mean, they
had like cameras, I guess, and they
would watch them. They would sing, you
know, they would they would turn around.
They would go like this to not face the
marshmallow to try to dist try to
distract themselves. They would pick up
the marshmallow and smell it
and put it back down, right? They would
just do all kinds of thing. Look at how
tortured this picture in the middle is.
Do you see this poor kid? Oh, and the
one right here next to me is smelling
it.
They would do all kinds of things to
distract themselves to try not to eat
the marshmallow.
And so literally there was all kinds of
responses. So from being able to wait
all 15 minutes to some kids the person
walked out the room, they grabbed the
marshmallow, they put it in their mouths
immediately.
So there was a spectrum of responses.
And the interesting thing about this
study is that they followed these kids
for years through school, high school,
college into adult life.
That's what's very um revealing and very
um very good because that's what was
valuable in the sense that it showed
what happened later. And this is what
I'm going to tell you about. So, what
happened with kids?
What happened with the kids that did
have self-control? First of all, so
that's what I'm going to talk about
first. So, the kids who did have
self-control. So, this and other
experiments, by the way, have found the
following with kids who do have
self-control. Kids who had self-control,
in other words, the ones who were able
to wait all 15 minutes, were found to be
happier and healthier,
have more satisfying relationships
that are longlasting.
They were able to earn more money and go
further in their careers.
They were able to handle stress,
conflict, and adversity.
They lived longer.
Self-control. Oh, watch. This is super
interesting. Okay. Self-control is a
better predictor of academic success
than intelligence. Did you hear? I'll
say it again. Self-control
is a better predictor of academic
success than intelligence.
And it is more important
in marital happiness, in other words,
happiness in your marriage
than empathy.
Of course, it is if you think about it,
because self-control means you're not
committing adultery, right?
Obviously. All right.
What happened with the kids who did not
have self-control? You want to know? Are
you curious?
I'll tell you.
People who well the adults who as kids
did did not have self-control. So, the
kids who ate the marshmallow either
immediately or didn't wait very long.
This is what happened. People with less
self-control had more economic, family,
and social problems, as you might
imagine,
but they committed more acts of violence
and crimes.
They had more debts, more addictions,
more psychological problems such as
depression and anxiety.
Uh other problems related to lack of
self-control were the following.
Sexually transmitted diseases,
uh more high blood pressure and strokes,
more alcoholism,
as I said, they were more violent crimes
and here are some of them. Uh homicide,
rape,
um they had more cancers as well. So,
um, they had more unwanted pregnancies.
Here's the thing. They committed more
adulteries. There were more divorces.
There were there was more unemployment,
more financial ruin, more family
problems.
And there was also more other types of
addiction. I had mentioned alcoholism
but there were other types of addictions
as well such as addiction behavioral
addictions such as addiction to
technology, pornography,
um that kind of thing. So the bottom
line is do you think it is important to
have self-control since childhood?
Do you think it's good for children to
learn to have self-control?
I would say
undoubtedly yes. Undoubtedly yes. All
right. So, but as we read that quote at
the beginning from Councils on Diet and
Food today, oh I mean that was written
back in the what 1800s early 1900s
but it seems like it was speaking into
the future. It was telling Tyra thank
you. You're saying yes about that
question. I think I think you agree.
Yes.
That quote that Ellen White wrote was
predict. Thank you Candy. Thank you very
much. That quote from Ellen White was
predicting I think today's environment
what Yale University you guys calls it.
You know, Yale University has come up
with a term
for today's environment when it comes to
appetite and self-control regarding
food. And I'm talking about just
regarding food. Of course, there's other
things that when she wrote about
appetite, she she wasn't just talking
about food. She was talking about
appetites of the flesh as the Bible
calls it, which involves a lot more than
just food. But in regards to food, there
is a center for the study of obesity or
whatever. at Yale and they have come up
with a term
and they called they call it the
obesoggenic environment
because
especially in developed countries we are
surrounded and bombarded with these
obesogenic foods which I wouldn't even
call them foods because they're not
foods really they are food like products
um and the reason why I don't call them
food is because if you look at the list
of ingredients, some of them I don't we
don't know what they are. If you don't
if you read ingredients and you don't
know what they are, are they really
foods?
If they're just chemicals and additives,
are they really foods? Can we call them
foods?
I don't know. I don't think they meet
the definition of food. Okay, but here's
the more worrying aspects of it. Okay,
I'm going to show you something that I
think is really boring and this is going
to be the theme of the next
presentation, but I'm just going to give
you an advance uh of it. Look at this
news uh uh story
study.
This is just a headline. Study sugar
hidden. That's the operative word here.
Sugar
hidden.
Hidden, you guys. Hidden. Because look
at the picture. These aren't candies.
This isn't cake.
Look at the picture.
Right. Sugar hidden in what?
What kind of food?
Junk. What's the other word for junk
again?
Trash
sugar hidden in junk food is how many
times?
Are you seeing what I'm seeing?
Eight times more what?
More what? You guys
addictive.
Do you see why Ellen White was warning
us a hundred years ago? Junk candy.
Thank you. Do you see why Ellen White
was warning about appetite? Do you see
why Satan has a stronghold on us through
appetite?
This is a plan.
Satan knows what he's doing.
He's so smart.
He has the whole world under his
control. And this is one of his most
powerful tools
to keep us under his control. Yes, it is
mind-blowing, Roselin. Yes, it is
mindblowing.
This is literal drug and it is so
socially acceptable
because who's going to go to
Thanksgiving meal and say, "Hey, aren't
you going to have another
I don't know what they call it. Aren't
you going to have some more cocaine?
Come on, have some more
birthday party. Come on. Aren't you
going to have some more heroin? Come on.
have some more heroin. Nobody's gonna be
saying that.
You go to church,
nobody's gonna have a whole table of
cocaine, heroin, and meth,
right?
But sugar
is eight times more addictive.
And we have whole tables of it
at church.
Sorry I'm sounding so controversial. I
get kind of upset about this.
I'm sorry if I sound so judgmental. I'm
so sorry. But I am addicted to it and I
have a hard time going to a church. I
get invited to give presentations and
there's my cocaine.
So, sorry if I sound upset,
but there it is. My own heroin is right
there in front of me.
And it is eight times more addictive
because it's not just an exaggeration.
It says study. That's the first word.
Sugar does have withdrawal symptoms,
Candy. Yes, you are correct.
Of course, it's withdrawal symptoms. It
is a drug.
That's why people have a hard time
stopping eating it.
If it wasn't a drug, it wouldn't have
withdrawal symptoms.
Here's the study.
It's not the only one, by the way.
Here's the study. That's why I tell you
from the very beginning of my
presentations,
I'm not just talking here. I show you
the the pyramid from the very beginning.
I'm not just giving you the bottom
stuff. I'm giving you the top. I'm
giving you actual evidence. This has
been studied. And here's the picture of
the of the researchers, you guys.
There's the rat in the front.
You know what they did
to show that this is eight times more
addictive?
I know it's kind of cruel to animals.
It's okay. It's serious. Yes. Thank you,
Candy. Thank you.
I'm so sorry, but I do get a little bit
upset. Anyway, I wrote my doctoral
present uh doctoral dissertation on on
um food addictions. This is how how
personal it is for me. Anyway, but this
is what these people did, okay? They
took the rats and they made them
addicted to cocaine. To what? To
cocaine.
They were addicted.
And then they put them probably in a
cage or something. And once they were
already addicted to cocaine,
then they they were already trained to
get the cocaine. They probably had some
levers. You know how they they they they
trained them to get the cocaine. Then
they put them exposed to both the
cocaine and the sugar.
And they went once they had learned to
that the other lever had the sugar.
Well, they went for the sugar eight more
times. You know, I found an actual
cartoon of this. Incredibly, people.
There's that cartoon.
Can you believe it?
Somebody made a cartoon of this.
Give me some of what that white magic.
Sugar is a white powder and so is
refined
flour.
Just like cocaine is a white powder, you
guys.
White powder.
Wow. If you think about it, that's kind
of interesting. They couldn't stop.
That's right.
So, that's how they figured out that
sugar
is eight times more addictive. There's
another point, you guys.
The junk food
that is out there that is particularly
difficult to resist
is usually a combination of fat and
sugar.
Fat and sugar. Desserts for instance.
And if you think about it, there's
nothing in nature
that has sugar and fat combined. Because
if you think about this, in nature you
do find things that have fat or that
have sugar. But in processed foods, they
put them together. In nature, we have
fat like avocados, seeds
separate
from the sugar. We have sugar. By the
way, these foods also have fiber,
phytonutrients, minerals, chemicals.
They're valuable. They're nutritious for
us, but they don't have the sugar and
the fat combined.
But in processed foods, they put them
together
in way higher amounts. By the way,
there's no nutrition value here because
there's no minerals, no vitamins, no
phyitochemicals, no fiber,
and high amounts of sugar and fat. way
higher than the foods up above here.
The starch converts to sugar. Yes.
Because these this starch has no fiber.
This starch has no fiber. It's very
different from whole grain starch. The
whole grain starch is encased in fiber
and it acts in synergy with all the
other nutrients.
Whereas this starch is empty calories,
very very different. Your body process
these foods very different. And when
your tongue touches that sugar, it's a
hit directly to the brain and stimulates
the dopamine
system in the brain the exact same way
as any other drug. And that's what I
will be talking about two weeks from
today. Food addiction and I will explain
the neuroscience behind it which is the
same as any other addiction. So the same
um science behind food addiction is the
exact same as alcohol addiction, drug
addiction, cigarette addiction, porn
addiction, any behavioral addiction is
the same as substance addiction,
substance use disorder and is the same
as food addiction. So all the addictions
have the same commonality in the brain
which is an alteration of the dopamine
system and that's what I will talk about
two weeks from today. So I hope you
don't miss it. It's very important to
understand this because there is a cure
and the cure is in the eight principles
of health is one of those principles.
So I hope you don't miss it. But there's
also another aspect and it's sometimes
that we use food to medicate our
emotions and this is where eating
disorders are born because we use food
to medicate ourselves
when we have depression, anxiety
and we don't have control of our
emotions. s lack of self-control.
We eat for emotional reasons and we
repeat these
behaviors over and over and over again.
This is very very very
dangerous
especially in adolescence as you
probably know it can lead to serious
eating disorders. This is you know this
last week this is not very common. I
don't know what's happening. I don't
know what's happening. But this last
week, I got two moms, two mothers who
called me for the exact same reason.
This is This doesn't happen to me very
often, but two mothers called me for the
exact same reason. Two young girls the
similar age
that are having these issues.
And I think it has to do with social
media
and peer pressure at school,
but it's getting really bad. It's
getting really really bad. The I don't
know. I don't know. But uh
this is a problem and what I think is
the one of the solutions is that parents
need to provide a safe environment with
healthy foods from birth if possible but
from very very young and to provide that
healthy environment so that young kids
are not scared of their weight. If kids
are scared of their weight, they're
going to restrict.
And the reason why they're uh
restricting is because they're scared of
gaining weight. And they're gaining
weight because they're eating junk food.
Yeah. So anyway, how do we do this?
Well, anyway, I today what I really want
to u finish off is by giving you the
nine keys, what I've learned are the
some of the best ways to achieving your
goals. How do you Okay, first of all,
you have to set goals.
for your health. So, we talked about
diabetes, blood pressure, cholesterol.
Do you have any of these that are too
high? So, I do 10day programs as I uh
mentioned in my work. So, we measure uh
total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol. Uh
some doctors measure something called
Apo B, which is another way to measure
bad cholesterol. You can measure uh
triglycerides. Sometimes people have
those high as well. Uh your glucose or
your A1C, that's a way to measure how
much sugar is in your blood. Uh blood
pressure.
Uh also, of course, weight, which is not
is not it doesn't have to do with how
good you look. It has to do with your
health because carrying extra weight
that atapost tissue in your body is
uh inflammatory. That adipose tissue in
the body releases cytoines, inflammatory
cytoines that elevate inflammation in
your body. Also, by the way, that extra
cyto uh adopose tissue releases also
hormones for both males and females, and
I'm talking about estrogen in
particular. So, males that carry extra
weight have extra estrogen. You know,
sometimes men think that if they drink
soy milk, they're going to get male
boobs. No, the male boobs don't come
from drinking soy milk. They they come
from the fat tissue because it produces
extra estrogen.
Anyway, all this also cancer risk. The
adipose tissue produces cancer risk. We
already talked about the insulin
resistance. Anyway, so all of this extra
weight is a health risk. Okay? So, we
need to set oursel health goals and to
build self-control to be able to achieve
those health goals. So, today I'm going
to talk about nine steps or keys to be
able to achieve those. So, I'm going to
go through them. Are you ready to write?
Or you can watch this again if you don't
catch them. But I think these throughout
the years and also studying, you know,
some of the health behavior, these are
ways you you can achieve that. Okay. So
number one, one of the first ways to do
it first of all is to find your why.
This is very important. You have to find
your inner motivation.
How do you do that though? Well, you
know, sometimes as Christians
wanting to glorify God in our bodies, we
have sometimes a spiritual reason to do
that. But sometimes you also have an
more inner reason. You have to keep
asking yourself, why do I want to do
this? And and once you give yourself a
reason, but why do I want to do this?
You know why? And keep asking yourself
until you find the innermost reason
um for that.
So keep asking yourself until you find
the last reason, the most inner reason,
and then put that somewhere. Put it in
front of your mirror in the morning or
put it on on the on the fridge maybe or
somewhere where you can face it every
single day to remind yourself so that
when you are tempted
to maybe you know have something that
you shouldn't or maybe you're don't want
to get up to go for a walk or something
you're able to remind yourself of your
why. But another way that helps
sometimes is to make a list of the pros
and cons. So that way you can that maybe
use your thinking process to motivate
yourself.
By the way, in behavioral health,
behavioral science, there is a theory of
behavioral change called the stages of
change. And it's very interesting how
sometimes people who don't even want to
change that's called the
precontemplation
stage when you don't even ah no no I
don't want to I don't want to change my
diet at all. No no no don't even talk to
me about your diet. No.
How do you get a person to move from
that precontemplation
stage to maybe think, well, maybe I
should,
you know, maybe I I do really need to
think about how I should change my diet
or start exercising or something. How do
you move that needle?
And what I have found is that the more
people are exposed
to health information. And it doesn't
have to be that people are nagging them
all the time, but maybe going to a
health presentation,
listening to something maybe like this,
a health presentation on Facebook, on
YouTube, at a church,
watching, you know, a documentary,
the more people hear, sometimes you
think they're not listening.
You don't even know if that seed is
planted
and months from now, years from now that
seed may yield fruit. The more people
listen, sometimes it seems like it's not
giving any results, but you don't know.
So just even for yourself, expose
yourself to more and more information so
that someday that will make a
difference. So that leads to number two
which is the inspiration.
I recommend watch all the documentaries
that you can. Forks Over Knives is a
classic now. I recommend everybody watch
it.
It was produced in 2011 I think. Um and
it's a classic. It's It's now a classic
because it's one of the first ones that
really
started off this movement in plant-based
nutrition. And if you watch it, it might
change your life. So, warning, it might
change your life. Uh, it's a great
movie. I think documentaries um are one
of those things that can really change a
person's life. So, I recommend watching
them. Honestly, I do. I do. So, if you
if you have someone in your life that
you're worried about their health or
something, maybe offer to sit down with
them. Hey, let's watch this on a
Saturday night or something, you know,
just offer to watch one of these. So,
these are the ones that I really, really
recommend. There's more. I just have a
couple here that um that I put on on in
this presentation that I think are
really, really good, but there's
actually a few more that uh that are out
there that are just as good. But this is
a classic, Forks Over Knives. There's
another one called What the Health and
it's excellent. It's really
inspirational. And the most
inspirational part of these
documentaries o obviously is the
testimonials. So you see people's lives
being transformed and their health being
just like, wow, amazing testimonials.
and the one that inspired my work. So,
our job, we do a 10day
um intervention, if you will, like a
10-day challenge, and people change, you
know, their biometrics in only 10 days.
And like I told you, I've seen people's
LDL drop 10, 20, 30, 40% or more. Same
with glucose, same with total
cholesterol, blood pressure. I mean,
amazing results. Well, this was all born
from a documentary actually which was uh
this is the documentary that I'm this is
it plant pure nation
and in this uh documentary you see
exactly that they go to South Carolina I
think or North Carolina I don't remember
I think it's South Carolina and it was
produced by the son of Dr. T. Colin
Campbell. If you've ever read the China
Study,
that's the author. T. Colin Campbell is
the author of The China Study. Pretty
famous man. His son Nelson Campbell
produced this documentary. And Nelson
Campbell started after this documentary
that was pretty successful. He started
this network of groups around the
country that do 10-day programs. And the
10-day program is all called Community
RX. Our program is called Community RX.
We're in the middle of a program right
now called Community RX. And they're
10-day programs. And so in this uh
movie, you you basically see that how
that works. So they and they had more
money than we do. So they actually take
the biometrics at the beginning. They
take their, you know, their cholesterol,
glucose and triglycerides, all this
stuff. And then they give them the food
throughout the 10 days. They actually
give them the food. The people pick up
the food every day. And at the end of
the 10 days, they give the bio they do
the biometric testing again. And you see
their faces like, "What? I've never seen
my triglycerides this low in my whole
life." Ah, so it's really inspirational
what can happen in only 10 days. By the
way, that's in the Bible. So, as you
know, read chapter one of Daniel if you
want to see in the Bible. Anyway,
recommend it. Highly recommend it. At
least these three. So, where did where
do you find inspiration? documentaries,
films, classes, go to cooking classes,
programs like this one or other ones at
church presentations at church at
YouTube or whatever things like this.
So, this is where you find this kind of
inspiration. Seek it, search for it.
Okay. Number three is determination.
Anything is possible if you have the
intelligence and the willpower to make
it happen. But you need God's help
obviously for that. Okay. So, but this
is how I think of it as the termin. What
is determination?
When a bride is going and I've heard
this story over and over again, so I
know this happens in this real. When a
bride wants to fit into
a certain size of dress by her wedding
date and let's say there's six months to
that wedding date and she needs to lose
a certain amount of pounds, you can put
all the donuts in the world in front of
that bride, all the cake, all the pizza,
and all the stuff in the world. But if
she is determined to fit into that
dress, it doesn't matter. She will do
it. You see, that's determination. When
you have something in your mind that you
want to do, you will do it. And you know
what the Bible talks about that? Let us
not become weary in doing good.
For at the proper time, we will reap the
harvest if we do not give up.
Galatians 6:9.
You can have this. Put it in your
fridge.
I'm just saying fridge if that's you
know your goal has to do with your
fridge maybe. Okay. Next thing is to set
those goals. Okay. Goals are very
important. Do you need to lower your
glucose? Okay. That's a goal. Write it
down.
Do you know that the difference between
the people who achieve their goals and
th and those who do not is that the
people who achieve the their goals write
them down. Do you know that CEOs that
make millions of dollars a years have
coaches and pay those coaches hundreds
of thousands of dollars a year and those
coaches tell them you have to write down
your goals. They literally paid these
people hundreds of thousands of dollars
a years to tell them this one thing.
Write down your goals.
And these goals have to be smart goals.
You know what smart stands for, right?
You know this concept of smart goals.
Smart goals have to follow these rules.
They have to be specific.
Meaning I want to lose weight. Okay. Or
no, no, no, wait. A non nonspecific goal
would be I want to be healthy.
That's not specific. I want to lose
weight would be specific. But I want to
be healthy. That's too vague.
Needs to be specific in the sense that
it needs to be measurable. The M stands
for measurable. You have to be able to
measure it. Health is not measurable,
but weight is measurable. Cholesterol is
measurable. Glucose is measurable.
Things that are measurable are specific.
Also, it needs to be attainable because
if you say, I want to lose 100 pounds in
a month,
that's not attainable. You cannot lose
that kind of weight. Okay. I want to
drop my cholesterol from 300 to 150 in
two weeks. Okay,
that's kind of crazy.
Do things are attainable, realistic,
relevant. Okay, if you have
diabetes
and your goal is to read a a book a
week, okay, that's a great goal, but
let's stick to what's needed at the
moment. Okay, I mean, maybe that goal is
great, too. Maybe that's you want to do
that too. But how about we think about
health goals at the moment because your
diabetes is maybe what needs attention
at the moment. So that's what's
relevant. That's just an example I'm
giving you. Okay? And the last thing is
time based. Set a date.
Set a date by when. If you don't set a
date, it might never happen.
It might never happen. So set a date.
That's how you get it done.
So make yourself a little worksheet and
write those things down. If you don't
write them, it might never happen. Write
them down. Even put a signature. Even
have a witness. Have a witness.
Your child, your best friend, your
parent, your spouse.
Accountability.
Some have an accountability partner that
will help.
All right. So, that's how you get it
done.
Do not super long-term goals. Make them
somewhat
medium to short because if they're way
too long in the future, then they might
never happen either.
All right? So, set them to be somewhat
medium to short term. Okay. The next one
is to plan ahead. This is extremely
important if you really want to get your
goals
uh achieved. You need to plan and
especially when it comes to healthy
eating and exercise. People don't
realize how important it is to do this.
They really underestimate this one.
Planning ahead is vital. Vital,
especially with these things. What are
you going to do for next Thanksgiving?
Especially if your family is not on the
same page. You might need to take food.
Take food. You know, I've been doing
this for years. My family eats my food.
Sometimes I eat all of my food that I
take for Thanksgiving. I'm like, "Hey, I
thought you guys weren't,
you know, eating all that. How come I
don't have any leftovers? You guys have
so much leftovers. I don't have any
because you guys ate all my food. It's
fine. It's okay. They're eating healthy
food, so it's fine. I don't care
anymore.
Make sure you are paying attention.
Family gatherings, holidays, plan ahead.
Take food.
Meal events with co-workers.
Stay away from those donuts if they take
too many donuts to work. Hanging out
with old friends. All of these things.
Plan ahead. Plan ahead.
Plan ahead. have non-negotiables.
Okay?
So, plan ahead for social gatherings,
plan ahead for all these things,
parties, all of these. When you're going
to eat at a restaurant, this is what my
husband and I do. We look up the
restaurants, look up the menu,
and if they don't have anything you
could eat, just go at a different
restaurant. If you're traveling,
whatever cities you're going to stop by,
this is what we do. We're already used
to it. We We're taking a a a road trip.
We look up all the cities in the middle,
you know, on the way and we like, okay,
this, you know, we look up Yelp or
whatever, and we look up the
restaurants, okay, we already know where
we're going to go.
On the planes, we take our own food. If
we're going to long international travel
or whatever, we request vegan foods and
we still take food just in case because
sometimes the food is no bueno.
That's what we do. Okay? So, you plan
ahead. Don't go for fat diets, okay?
Just go with God's diet all the time.
That's not a fat diet. For forget about
marketing, advertising, all that stuff.
Have a worksheet or something. Make sure
you know when you're going to be
exercising. That's a non-negotiable.
God made your body to move.
With the sweat of thy brow, you shall
eat.
God made you to eat and sweat, not just
All right, put it in your calendar.
That's a non-negotiable.
What are you going to be eating for
breakfast, lunch, and dinner all week?
Have a prep day. Which of these days is
going to be your prep day?
Make a dressing. Maybe on Sundays,
that's your prep day. Cut all your
veggies for the week and make your your
dressing for your salad. So that way
during the week, you just go Boop. Salad
done. Dressing store already there.
And cook your healthy meals if you need
to. Have a big pot of beans or
something. Make your foods ahead of time
if you need to. So that way throughout
the week, you don't have to stop at that
fast food restaurant.
Because when it's 12:30, 1:00 p.m., and
you're hungry for lunch, and you haven't
prepped anything,
what are you going to do?
It's so much easier to just go through
that drive-thru if you're hungry. If
you're hungry, whereas if you already
have it prepped ahead of time, no
thinking. There's no thinking necessary.
It's already done.
See,
make sure you know when you're going to
be doing your strengthening exercise,
your cardio,
all of that ahead of time. All right.
Next one is perseverance.
Don't give up.
If something doesn't come easy, the
average person will give up. That's why
they remain average. You know, the best
example in the Bible of perseverance, I
think, is Job.
Best example. He left us this.
The righteous shall hold on his way.
Hold on. Don't give up. Now, some of the
things that help us to persevere, I
think, is to join a group, to have some
social support.
It's very motivating.
It helps you to feel,
you know, part of something. It helps
when you feel isolated.
Online groups are just as good as in
person, by the way. And if there's not
one, then you start one.
Start a group in your own house, in the
local church.
This is a perfect
ministry opportunity.
This is me, by the way, doing a cooking
class.
start a cooking class
or a Bible study on health or a Bible
study, whatever. I'm just saying this is
a perfect ministry opportunity.
Perfect. But the key for this ministry
to be successful is consistency.
I mean in in the terms of ministry as in
evangelism for health ministry to be
successful evangelistically speaking is
consistency. It needs to be done
regularly and that's how it will work so
that people know that it will happen
once a month or once uh every other week
or whatever. It's the consistency that
will make it successful as a ministry.
All right. Number seven. Oh, four and
five. Okay. So candy four was number
four was to set goals.
That's number four. Set goals and make
sure they are smart goals.
Specific, measurable, attainable,
relevant, and timebased. Okay. And
number five is to plan ahead.
Make sure you plan ahead for special op
uh special events espec uh especially
um okay so let me show you I'm I'm
thinking I'm going through all of these
okay so plan ahead and special
especially for social roadblocks and for
environmental roadblocks such as you
know eating at a restaurant all these
things traveling those things are
important make a chart
um for planning ahead throughout the
week. That's number five. Plan ahead.
Okay.
Okay. So number seven is to form habits.
Forming habits
is making things automatic.
So when you create a habit,
you don't need willpower anymore. For
instance, when you do exercise every
morning, it becomes automatic. You just
grab those tennis shoes and you go for a
walk. That's just an example, okay? It's
the same thing that happens when you're
a child
and when you're like two or whatever,
you don't have the habit to brush your
teeth. And I had the hardest time to
teach my daughter how to brush your
teeth for it to become habit. You know
what I mean? At first, she just fought
me for years. she don't want to brush
her teeth
and uh uh can you give us some
guidelines on exercise? Okay, guidelines
on exercise. That's very good question.
I would say the ideal on exercise. Let's
go back to this picture on exercise
because these ladies, this is a picture
from Honduras and uh these ladies were
exercising probably after many years of
not exercising and um we would take them
for walks first and the cardio part. The
cardio part I think is extremely
important. That's for the heart. Cardio
means you know it comes from the root
word for heart and cardio I think is
necessary at least I would say well the
so the minimal recommendations are 150
minutes a week
I'd say that's too low but okay you can
start building up from 150 minutes a
week I'd say the more the better that's
why you know I I always cite that uh
Bible verse that says with the sweat of
thy brow you shall eat. So that means
that when we eat, we should sweat too
the same day hopefully. Uh but I think
walking every day is a really good
practice. Uh 30 minutes a day for
instance or more if possible. For
diabetics, the best time to eat is after
meals. So if you break up those 30
minutes into 10 minutes after every
meal, if you eat three times a day, 15
minutes after every meal for you twice a
day, uh but if you can after every meal,
that's ideal for diabetics. If you're
not diabetic, anytime you can walk, if
if whatever works with your lifestyle,
your schedule, whatever works before
meal or before breakfast is the best
time for burning fat if you are trying
to lose weight. So, you know, if that
works with you, if you're really
struggling with losing those last 10
pounds before breakfast would be ideal
because that's when you're fasted, so
you're into that burning fat burning uh
mode, if you will. So, if you can do fit
it in before breakfast, it super great.
But if not, don't worry about it. Do at
whatever time it fits. You know, it
doesn't matter if what's matters is
doing it. That's the most important
part. So, cardio, when it comes to
resistance exercise, I think it's vital
to do it as well. It needs to be part of
your your life because our ancestors did
it as part of their lifestyle. They
simply did it because they had to. They
had to work outside in the fields. They
had to grow their own food. They had to
cut wood. They had to carry heavy the
wood, you know, they had to the women
had to wash the clothes by hand and then
carry the wet clothes. So they had to
carry weight. So they had to use their
muscles way more than us. We lose muscle
3 to 8% a decade. Every decade after the
age of 30, we are losing muscle unless
we're doing resistance exercise. We
absolutely have to prevent that through
resistance exercise. Minimum I would say
three times a week minimum but if you
haven't done it for years and years and
years you should start with two times a
week uh maybe 30 minutes start slow
start very mightly use bands or use your
own weight your own you know body weight
um so start you know go to a doctor
first if you're a certain age but we
absolutely need to be doing resistance
exercise uh consult with your doctor go
you know if you've had any um any
injuries, go to maybe a uh uh physical
therapist. You know, make sure you're
not injuring yourself, but everybody
should be at least preventing further
muscle loss. So, put it in the schedule.
Make sure you get enough guideline, but
everybody should be at the very least
preventing further muscle loss, but
everybody should be doing both kinds. So
it and it should become a habit so that
it becomes automatic just like brushing
your teeth so that way you're not
thinking about it. Don't don't don't uh
don't wait any longer. Make it a habit.
People started getting sick when air
conditioning was invented.
So much nicer to stay indoors because
it's nice temperature. Nice temperature
inside. Right. You're absolutely right,
Candy. All right. So, let's make
exercising
the automatic part of our lives. Same
with eating a big salad. Eat a big green
salad every day. And when you take the
old bad habits out, put a new one in.
Don't leave a vacuum in there. If you
leave a vacuum, that old habit's going
to come back. So, replace that habit
with something new. Put something in
there. That's good. All right. Number
eight is get support from your family.
Get help if you professional help if you
need it. But if you're starting
something new and your family is not in
the same page, at least let them know
because the last thing you need is for
your family to sabotage your attempts.
Uh so at the very least, I mean this is
the hard part. Honestly, this could be
very difficult sometimes, but you know,
sometimes we can get our family to at
least
not sabotage her in our attempts, you
know, out of love hopefully, right?
You know, one time I remember seeing one
of those episodes from those shows, My
600 pound life. I don't know if you
remember any of you remember this is a
terrible show of very large people my
600 lb life and there was one lady who
was really really really trying to lose
weight because she was like 600 lb and
her husband who wasn't 600 lb her
husband would bring junk food to the
house because he didn't want her to lose
the weight there was a codependence here
I mean that would be worst case scenario
hopefully that's not the days. So,
you know, hopefully there will be some
support in the house and hopefully the
best thing would be that the whole
family is on the same page. Um, but you
know, you can always say, "Hey, my
doctor said I need to do this. My
nutritionist said I need to do this. Can
you please recommend a particular
YouTube channel or online group that we
can exercise with daily or at least
until we get to understand or learn a
routine?" Well,
pastor um our pastor is doing this.
Pastor Ivra Myyers is doing an exercise
group. So, I would say join Pastor
Meyers.
I would say he is awesome. He's been
doing well, I don't know what exactly
he's been doing because I haven't been
able to join it to ask to follow with
him. I personally,
as a woman, I've been doing a program
called V Fit and it's just for women.
Um, but she only does it a few times a
year and right now she's not doing it
actively, but she does have like um like
um an an app and um so I you know you
keep doing the app and she has these um
these uh uh workouts in the apps and she
also has her um recipes and she has
different things in the app but it's
mostly for women. So, these are workouts
for women and the recipes are all vegan.
Uh, so that's what I've been doing for
because, you know, I didn't know the
pastor was going to be doing anything.
This is very recent. So, I've been doing
this for like two or two years or
something. And um and it's it's for
women. Um, so there's that, too. There's
there's some programs out there. I've
seen also one called Vegan Gym. I
haven't uh followed him very closely. I
think these are two guys that are
European, I think. Uh, but I've seen
Vegan Gym um out there. So, there's some
people out there doing stuff. Not that I
know too much about it. Oh, it's called
V V with V Fit. And this is for girls,
for ladies. Um, so anyway, V Fit. and
she's in Florida
and I so again I I I just discovered
this other people called Vegan Gym or
something like that. Uh but Pastor Myers
is doing it. So why not join Pastor
Myers? I think
probably the best probably the best
person to to join. Um but anyway for the
other thing is for food or something
ministry opportunity you guys
you can start something start something
if you don't find what you want you can
always start something all right last
thing is always the most important is to
trust in God do you know that uh AA
alcoholics anonymous or other 12step uh
programs uh they rely on, you know, they
call it the higher power um because
everybody not everybody who goes there
is Christian. But this is such an
important part of their philosophy, you
know, having to not rely on yourself
basically to recognize that you can't do
this on your own, you know, to to be
able to um
be able to stop drinking or stop
whatever addiction you have. You can't
do this on your own. But I have found
uh in the scientific literature
this super interesting. It says
religion. Do you see this? Are you
reading this? It says religion
replenishes
self-control. Wow. Religion replenishes
self-control. In this study, they found
the participants who were given a
sentence containing five words to
unscramble and some contained religious
themes and others did not. And after
unscrambling the sentences, the
participants were asked to complete a
number of tasks that required
self-control. Basically, that's what
they did. Uh so some of them enduring
discomfort, delayed gratification,
exerting patience and refraining from
impulsive responses. And the
participants who had unscrambled the
sentences containing religious themes
had more self-control in completing
their tasks. And the the author said,
"Our most interesting finding was that
religious concepts were able to refuel
self-control
after it had been depleted by another
unrelated task. In other words, even
when we found when we would predict
people to be unable to exert
self-control after completing
religiously themed tasks, they defied
logic and were able to muster
self-control. Until now, I believe, so
this is one of the authors. I believed
religion was a matter of faith. People
had little practical use for religion.
This research actually suggests that
religion can serve in a very useful
function in society.
People can turn to religion not just for
transcendence and fears regarding death
and afterlife but also for practical
purposes.
That's what the author said.
Wow. Wow. Wow. Okay. This other study
says
religious. So the the title religious
self-regulation and self-control
associations explanations and
implications and in this study
um the reviews oh this study reviews the
different
effects that religious of religious
practices such as prayer on
self-regulation and self-control.
And
if you go further, you know, you read
more into the study itself, you go down
into more in detail into the study
itself,
they found that prayer does have an
effect on the brain's neuroscircuits.
And when neuroscientists observe people
praying and meditating, they see strong
activity in two parts of the brain that
they're also important in
self-regulation
and control of attention.
They found that prayer meditation
rituals are kind of anorobic exercise
for self-control.
Wow.
So there's science behind this you guys.
Prayer
helps with selfont control.
Is that amazing?
I think it is. So God has given us
not a spirit of fear but of love and
power and selfontrol.
That's in first Timothy but I forgot the
exact
second Timothy. And I forgot the chapter
51 17 something like that. But anyway, I
wanted to
give you this the nine ways to
I hope this was helpful. I want to give
you my website again,
healthforttoday.net.
Because in this website, as I've told
you many times, you can do the 10day
program. If you really want to improve
your health, you can
uh do 10 days to better health at least
your diet. You can find in this website,
the 10day challenge. This is by the way
my website in Spanish because it's also
in Spanish. Salutarawunto.com.
Okay. So, healthfor.net
and salute punto
and you can improve your health in 10
days. I already went through the whole
fourpart
uh series on diabetes and how it is
related to insulin resistance which is
the root cause for both diabetes but
also all the complications that come
with the insulin resistance.
Okay. So you want me to put the Oh, I
don't know if I can put it in the chat.
I don't know if maybe our How do I put
it in the other chat? I don't know how
to do it.
I need it.
I don't know how to put it in that chat,
you guys.
It's healthfor.net or salto.
And I don't know how to Oh, in Facebook,
you mean? Oh, I can do it. I can put it
in Facebook. I'll put it I'll put it on
Facebook when this broadcast is over.
Don't worry, Miranda. Miranda way upon
it. Okay, don't worry about it. I will
put it in Facebook and salute.
No problem, Miranda. Don't worry about
it. I will put the I think you want the
the um I think you want the website,
right? I think you want the website.
Don't worry about it, Miranda. I will
put it. Okay. So
if you need any other any other uh help
you can contact me in any one of these
two websites health for today or salute
paroi.com
either the English or the Spanish. Oh
there it is. Um our producer put it up
for you you guys. So thank you guys. I
think our producer can take out if you
want uh the take it out of the the
screen. But thank you guys for being
here with us
and uh we'll see you in two weeks. Two
weeks.
I will be speaking about food addictions
in two weeks. So invite your friends
because I think we will close the um the
cycle on this very important topic. Um I
think it's
there it is. Okay. Um I think it's very
important to finish this kind of talking
about food addictions. Okay. Because
we've been talking about diabetes, we've
been talking about insulin resistance
and we've been talking about all the
different complications. We tal we
finished the four uh part series on the
diabetes and insulin resistance and it's
all about food and of course we will be
continue to talk about health and food
related issues right but I wanted to
finish with these two presentations
on the habits and self-control
to kind of give you a foundation on that
and then the next presentation will be
about food addiction which is a little
bit deeper into the neuroscience
of the food addiction
uh in particular because that's a little
bit a little bit deeper if you will and
a little bit you know a little bit
harder. Uh and it's you know it it is a
little bit more um it's a it's a it's a
it's a bit more you know to take if you
will. Okay, this is a little bit lighter
topic. That one is a little bit more uh
but I think it's it's it's very
important to understand because it is so
relevant nowadays. Food addiction is a
thing and it's going on.
So that's two weeks from today. I will
give you the date. It will be the
second, September 2nd. Uh so we'll be
sending you the slides for today's
presentation and September 2nd we will
do true health Tuesday and it will be on
food addictions which by the way is the
same as I said before is the same
principle behind all addictions. So once
we understand how to heal food addiction
is really the same principle behind all
addictions honestly. So can we do menu
planning? Yes. So that's why in
healthfor.net it. I give you a 10day
menu. Okay, 10day menu with recipes and
uh you can use that menu as a foundation
to then build on build on that and you
can do two weeks, you can do a month
ahead of time if you want. I definitely
recommend doing menu planning.
Definitely it it will change your life
because it makes things so much easier.
It makes things way much way easier if
you want to eat healthy. That way, you
know, you're not struggling last minute
on what am I going to eat? What am I
going to do? You can do shopping. By the
way, my 10day uh my 10day challenge
thing has a uh also a shopping list. So,
that can help too.
So, that way you know what to buy. So, I
try to make it easy for people. Okay.
So, it's an introduction. It's only 10
days, but then you can build on that.
Okay. So, thank you for being with us
once again. I hope this was helpful and
and educational. If you have any
questions, please contact me and my
website. You already hopefully wrote it
down. And we're going to finish today's
presentation with some prayer. And I
hope you have a wonderful, wonderful
evening. And don't forget to like and
subscribe to these channels and YouTube
and to connect with all the other uh
programming on living mana online
church. Okay. So let's finish with some
prayer.
Dear heavenly father, thank you so much
for giving us a chance to have this
presentation and for giving us this
wonderful health message that we can use
not only for our own health and our own
benefit to be able to take care of our
body temple, but also that we can share
with others so that they can achieve
better health and they can learn that
you are our God and creator and that
they can learn also how to glorify you
through their bodies. Be with us the
rest of this evening and the rest of
this week and uh help us to have wisdom
to uh so that we can care for our bodies
and uh and achieve better health. If we
have any diseases, I I ask Lord that if
anyone who is watching has any health
issues that you bless them Lord and put
your healing hands over them and their
families in Jesus name I pray. Amen.
Thank you once again you guys. See you
soon in two weeks and bless you and have
a good night.